布鲁图斯
Brutus.
多米那 多米那 别这样
Domina. Domina, please don't do that.
我很抱歉
I'm so sorry.
你为什么不去躺下休息？你已经十分疲倦了
Why don't you lie down? You're very tired.
是的…
Yes...
我已经…
I'm...
累极了
very tired.
你要喝点柳树汁吗？
Would you like some willow water?
我需要吗？
Would I?
能帮助你入睡
It will help you sleep.
不需要再睡了
No. No more sleep.
来吧 打起精神来
Oh, come along, cheer up.
你总不能在自己的婚礼上哭吧
You can't cry at your own wedding.
给她看看她有多漂亮
Show her how lovely she looks.
- 我看起来真恐怖 - 不 你漂亮着呢
- I look horrid. - No, you're beautiful.
噢 天啊 还在哭
Gods, still weeping.
为了安排这个婚礼我可是招了不少麻烦
I went to a lot of trouble to arrange this marriage.
别给我弄砸了
Please don't ruin it.
没有多少男人肯娶一个 一文不值的孤儿
There's not many men willing to marry a penniless orphan.
我很抱歉 我很感激
I'm sorry. I am very grateful.
只不过… 我肯定他是个好男人
It's just... I'm sure he's a very nice man.
只不过我一直梦想的是
It's just, I had always imagined
我会嫁给一个…
I'd wed someone...
跟这个不一样的男人
Someone different.
要是你哭得脸红腮涨得出去 你谁也嫁不了
You won't wed anyone at all if you come out all red and puffy.
我了解男人
I know men.
这个人会是一个好丈夫
And this one will make a lovely husband.
不论她生病或是健康 富有或贫穷
When and where you are Gaia,
我始终忠于她
there and then I am Gaius.
哦 对不起
Yes, sorry.
不论他生病或是健康 富有或贫穷
When and where you are Gaius,
我始终忠于他
then and there, I am Gaia.
[拉丁语] 主神丘庇特 女神朱诺 女神维纳斯
[拉丁语] 女神苏得拉 女神戴安娜
[拉丁语] 主神丘庇特 女神朱诺
[拉丁语] 女神维纳斯 女神苏得拉 女神戴安娜…
让人感慨颇多 对吧？
Makes you think, doesn't it?
- 感慨什么？- 婚姻啊
- About what? - About marriage.
- 是吗？- 我们俩
- Does it? - The two of us.
趁着占卜官还在 我们现在就可以把事儿办了
With the augur here, we might as well do it now.
简单又省时
Quick and simple.
我们俩结婚的时候 那一定是有史以来最棒的婚礼
When we get married, it'll have to be the best wedding ever seen.
只有这样才能与你相衬
You deserve nothing less.
我说说罢了
Just a thought.
这个占卜官动作跟蜗牛一样慢
This augur moves like a snail.
优利亚家族的阿提娅
Atia of the Julii,
我要求主持公道
I call for justice!
优利亚家族的阿提娅
Atia of the Julii,
我要求主持公道
I call for justice.
优利亚家族的阿提娅
Atia of the Julii,
我要求主持公道
I call for justice.
失陪一下
Excuse me for a moment.
优利亚家族的阿提娅
Atia of the Julii,
我要求主持公道
I call for justice.
优利亚家族的阿提娅
Atia of the Julii,
我要求主持公道
I call for justice.
优利亚家族的阿提娅
Atia of the Julii,
我要求主持公道
I call for justice.
优利亚家族的阿提娅
Atia of the Julii,
我要求主持公道
I call for justice.
优利亚家族的阿提娅
Atia of the Julii,
我要求主持公道
I call for justice.
- 优利亚家族的阿提娅 我要求主持公道 - 这滑稽的蠢货
- Atia of the Julii, I call for justice. - Ludicrous old bat.
- 我们该怎么办？- 优利亚家族的阿提娅 我要求主持公道
- What shall we do? - Atia of the Julii, I call for justice.
不怎么办 什么都不做
Nothing. Nothing at all.
只要我们无视她 她很快就走了
She'll go away soon enough if we just ignore her.
嗨 老婆
Hey, wife.
太阳都晒屁股了
Sun's been up for hours.
该起床了
It's time to get up.
马上
Soon.
不如趁此机会…
While we're here...
不
No.
你又不知道我要干吗？
You don't know what I was gonna ask.
你想做爱
You want to make love.
这想法不错
That's an idea.
对宝宝不好
No good for baby.
他不会介意的
He won't mind.
也许是个女孩
Maybe she.
那她一样不会介意
She won't mind, neither.
对宝宝不好 祭司说的
No good for baby. Priest says so.
祭司？祭司？
Priest? Priest?
什么祭司？
What priest?
我自己国家的祭司
Priest in my country.
噢 反正我们又不是在你的国家 对吧？
Well, we're not in your country, are we?
当宝宝会动了之后 就不可以瞎搞
When baby start to move, no love.
这是规矩
Is rules.
孩子在动？
The baby's moving?
是的 摸摸
Yes, feel.
我们别无选择 只能动用奥斯提亚里面的船坞
So we have no choice but to use the deeper berths in Ostia.
我们现有的谷物船 货运量已经超过10000罐了
We now have grain ships in excess of 10,000 amphorae.
哼 算盘可真精啊 那些船坞是留着给我们自己的油料船的
Tricky. Those berths have been reserved for our oil ships
很早以前就他妈是这规矩了
since fuck knows when, way back.
没理由说规矩不能变
Well, that's no reason to keep it so.
- 时代不同了 - 你一直这么说
- Times change. - So you keep saying.
我可以同意你使用我们的船坞
I'll allow you to use our berths,
不过我们要从中抽取5％的谷物
but we'll take 5% of the grain
装运要用我们的人
and the ships will be unloaded by my own men.
放屁 你们做强盗算了
Bollocks. That's a license for thievery.
说得好像我们不是一样
If we were thieves.
我可以让你抽取5％ 但是马修斯会被派去奥斯提亚
I'll give you the 5%, but Mascius will go down to Ostia
他将监管码头上的事
and he will supervise the dock work.
我今天就走
I'll leave today.
如你所愿
As you wish.
优利亚家族的阿提娅
Atia of the Julii,
我要求主持公道
I call for justice.
优利亚家族的阿提娅
Atia of the Julii,
我要求主持公道
I call for justice.
优利亚家族的阿提娅
Atia of the Julii,
我要求主持公道
I call for justice.
优利亚家族的阿提娅
Atia of the Julii,
我要求主持公道
I call for justice.
优利亚家族的阿提娅
Atia of the Julii,
我要求主持公道
I call for justice.
优利亚家族的阿提娅
Atia of the Julii,
我要求主持公道
I call for justice.
早上好各位
Good morning, all.
你迟到了
You're late.
伯斯卡昨天结婚
Posca's wedding yesterday.
我恐怕是喝多了
I'm afraid I drank rather too much.
我没办法起床 不管怎么样都不行
I could not get out of bed, no matter how hard I tried.
我头疼得要命
I have the most shocking headache.
所以你们俩得小声说话
So you must both speak very quietly
不然我的头就要炸成碎片了
or I shall shatter into a thousand little pieces.
一些…元老院的大人物 来找过我
I've been approached by a number of eminent friends among the Senate.
他们有点担心
They are troubled.
我倒不认为他们的忧虑 是必要的…
I do not say that they have grounds for anxiety,
不过我要不跟你们说一声的话 就是我的失职
but I feel I would be remiss if I did not communicate...
- 你就直说吧 - 好的 好的
- Do get on with it, man. - Yes, yes.
他们担心我们三个可能打算…
They're worried that perhaps we three intend
搞某种形式的…
to establish some form of...
暴政
tyranny.
是谁这么忧心忡忡？
And who are these worriers?
- 把名字给我 - 这可有点为难
- Give me names. - That's awkward.
他们是私下跟我说的
They spoke to me in confidence.
那是当然的
I'll bet they did.
你去告诉你那些尊贵的朋友 闭上他们的嘴
You tell your eminent friends to shut their mouths.
让他们去看看讲坛前西赛罗的手
Tell them to go look on Cicero's hands in the Forum
搞清楚那些乱嚷嚷暴政的人
and remember what happens
会有什么下场
to those that prattle of tyranny.
我提出来 是怕你们 认为我有所隐瞒
I only mention it. I would be remiss if I did not.
你是对的 莱彼德斯
You're quite right, Lepidus.
你是对的
Quite right.
现在我们可以开始谈正事了吗？
Now, shall we get down to business?
好的 该干嘛干嘛
Yes, by all means.
很明显我们三个不能同时统治罗马
Clearly, we three cannot all rule together at once.
彼此之间只会产生困惑和争执
We shall confuse and contradict each other.
- 这倒是实话 - 我们必须分担职责
- True enough. - We must divide responsibilities.
你有什么建议？
What are you proposing?
我建议我们把罗马的领土一分为三
I suggest we divide the territory of Rome into three.
每个人统治其中一块领地
Each one of us shall assume command of one region.
听起来很合理
Sounds reasonable.
可是要怎么分？
Who gets what?
我还没考虑到这一点
I haven't considered that yet.
不过罗马的核心组织错综复杂
But Rome is a very complex machine.
哪像切菜那么简单
One can't simply chop it up like cabbage.
罗马应该归你 还有西域
You should have Rome and the west.
我要的是… 埃及和东部的行省
And I will make do with Egypt and the eastern provinces.
- 如何？- 罗马和西域有什么？
- Objections? - Rome and the west has what?
好斗的高卢人 还有日耳曼人 一个难伺候的元老院
Rowdy Gauls, Germans, a fractious Senate,
还有整治黑帮的烂摊子
all the trouble of keeping the Roman mob happy.
东方才是聚宝盆
The east is where the money is,
粮食收成和税收的主要来源
the grain supply, most of the tax revenue.
所有的税收都应该平均分配
Well, all the revenues would be divided equally, of course.
这只是单纯的行政分管
It would be a purely administrative division.
所有的钱都统一收归国库
All monies would be held in a single treasury.
- 这样还行 - 那我呢？
- That would work. - And I?
我有什么？
What would I get?
是啊
Yes.
非洲
Africa.
优利亚家族的阿提娅
Atia of the Julii,
我要求主持公道
I call for justice.
优利亚家族的阿提娅
Atia of the Julii,
我要求主持公道
I call for justice.
优利亚家族的阿提娅
Atia of the Julii,
我要求主持公道
I call for justice.
优利亚家族的阿提娅
Atia of the Julii...
这算什么？难道她生了根不成？
What is this? Is she putting down roots?
优利亚家族的阿提娅
Atia of the Julii,
我要求主持公道
I call for justice.
优利亚家族的阿提娅
Atia of the Julii,
我要求主持公道
I call for justice.
优利亚家族的阿提娅
Atia of the Julii...
啊
So...
你今天过得怎么样啊？
How goes your day?
我可是好得不得了
Mine went extremely well.
她都快把我逼疯了 这不公平
She's driving me mad. It's completely unfair.
又不是我宰了她的宝贝儿子
It wasn't me who killed her precious son.
- 她应该在你家门外哭 - 她只不过想引人注意
- She should be wailing outside your house. - She just wants a little attention.
走出去 让她对你咆哮一阵
Go out. Let her rant at you a while.
那她很快就会走了
She'll soon leave.
在一群眉来眼去的下等人面前 接受她的诅咒？我才不要
And have her curse at me in front of a mob of ogling plebs?
我才不会让她称心如意呢
Never. I wouldn't give her that pleasure.
随便你
It's up to you.
不过我保证她不见到你 就不会离开的
But I guarantee she won't leave until she's seen you.
优利亚家族的阿提娅
Atia of the Julii...
别挤
Stop pushing!
等轮到你再说 你这女人
Wait your turn, woman!
我一家子都在要饭
My family is begging for food!
之前也见过你排队啊
Seen you on line before.
我？不可能
Me? No.
我看这个是假的
This looks like a fake to me.
我敢说你根本就 不住艾文台山 是吧？
I bet you don't even live on the Aventine.
不是假的 是真的 我对着神圣的黑石向你起誓
No fake. I swear to you by the sacred black stone.
滚出去 别让我在这附近再抓到你
Get out and don't let me catch you around here again.
滚
Get off!
你把木头搬来了吗？
Did you bring in wood?
- 还没 - 那去啊
- Not yet. - Go do.
- 不急 - 现在就去
- No hurry. - Get wood now.
自己搬去 我忙着呢
Get it yourself. I'm busy.
我命令你
I give you an order.
命令个屁
Kiss my ass.
来啊 试试看
Go ahead. Try.
我会把它塞进你嘴里
I'll shove it down your throat.
你会后悔的
You'll be sorry.
我丈夫会把你打成肉酱
My husband will beat you in pulp.
假的
Fake.
队伍里有一半 都是假的
Half the people in the line had them.
做得不错
Well made.
也有别的什么帮派想暗中闹事
Maybe one of the other collegia trying to fuck things up.
- 我想是莫密欧 - 很有可能
- Memmio, I expect. - Very likely.
- 我们该怎么做？- 什么也不做
- What do we do? - Nothing.
这我就不懂了
Lost me there.
莫密欧的确是又贪又不忠实
Memmio is dishonest and greedy.
我们怎么也没办法改变这个事实
Nothing we can do can change that.
如果他认为他能瞒过我们 随他高兴好了
If he thinks he's deceiving us, then he's happy.
我希望每个人都高兴
And I want everyone to be happy.
这就是我们的和平之道 无为而治
That's how we keep the peace. We do nothing.
可他在从我们手里偷东西
But he's stealing from us.
需要食物的人能够填饱肚子
People who need food are getting fed.
他们住在哪儿又有什么关系？
What matter where they live exactly?
你得去打死她
You must go to beat her dead!
- 冷静下来 打谁？- 那个婊子 那个盖娅
- Calm down. Beat who? - That whore, that Gaia.
- 去揍死她 - 她又干什么了？
- You beat her dead! - What's she done now?
她不肯照我说的搬来柴火 然后她说要把木棒塞进我喉咙里
She wouldn't bring in wood like I tell her. Then she say she'll choke me with a stick.
- 什么？- 她说要把木棒塞进我喉咙里
- What? - She say she's gonna choke me with a stick.
我不明白了 她为什么要这么做？你对她做了什么？
I don't understand. Why would she do that? What did you do to her?
哦 好极了 现在又成我的错了？
Perfect. Now it's my fault?
- 谢谢你 十分感谢 - 艾瑞纳
- Thank you. Thank you very much. - Eirene.
该死
Oh, cack.
我该怎么做？
What do I do?
- 别看我 - 好笑是吗？
- Don't look at me. - Very funny.
如果我去给盖娅应得的教训 你说马修斯会怎么想？
If I go and beat Gaia like she deserves, what do you think Mascius will do?
- 她是他的女人 对吧？- 这可是一团乱麻
- She's his girl. - It's a puzzle, all right.
马修斯去哪了？我该跟他用男人方式打招呼 他能自己去惩罚她
Where's Mascius? Maybe if I go and talk to him man to man, he can chastise her.
他在奥斯提亚 下个月才回
He's in Ostia.
- 新谷物船的事儿 - 该死
- The new grain-ship business. - Oh, cack.
也许你可以去揍她一顿
Maybe if you were to give her the beating...
如果你愿意的话我就去
I will if you want.
不 是我的老婆被人侮辱 这是我的事儿
No. It's my wife she insulted, my responsibility.
婚姻啊 真是复杂的东西
Marriage, it's complicated.
尤其她现在还怀孕了 我认为这让娘儿俩都有点想抓狂了
With her pregnant now... I think it drives them a little mad.
祝你生个大胖小子
Here's to a boy.
生个小子
A boy.
头儿
Chief.
这是要干什么？
What's that for?
别装了
Don't make a fuss now.
怎么？你准备鞭打我吗？
What? You're gonna whip me?
是的
I am.
你为什么要这么做？
Why would you want to do that?
你心里清楚得很
You know damn well why.
- 你说说看 - 你不尊敬我妻子
- Tell me. - You disrespected my wife.
哦 那个啊 她想打我
Oh, that. She tried to hit me.
她是这间屋子的女主人 你只是个该死的奴隶
She's lady of this house. You're a slave! She's allowed to hit you.
她有权打你 现在过来 让我们把这事儿了了
Now let's get it done.
只不过有点叫人难以想象 是她嫁给了老板
It's hard to remember she's married to the boss.
我是说不是针对她个人的 只是觉得有点不太合常理
I mean, nothing against her. It's just not natural.
她是个胆小如鼠的女人
She's such a mouse of a woman.
你却是男人中的雄狮
You're such a lion of a man.
胡扯 你根本不了解我们的事
Gerrae. You know nothing of us.
老鼠
Mouse.
雄狮 谁都看得出来
Lion. Anyone can see.
那你又是什么动物？
What sort of animal does that make you?
你希望我是什么动物？
What kind of animal do you want me to be?
会弯下腰去 毫无怨言地被鞭打的那种
The kind that will bend over and take her whipping without complaint.
我可以为你做到
I could do that for you.
但是你先得对我好一点
But you've got to treat me nice first.
给我闭嘴 知道了吗？闭嘴 过来
Just shut it, all right? Just shut it and come here.
你觉得马修斯发现你打了我 之后会干什么
What will Mascius do if you beat me?
我才不在乎马修斯会干什么
I don't give a fuck. Mascius will do what I tell him.
马修斯听我的 不 马修斯听我的
No, Mascius does what I tell him.
哦 真的？
Oh, yeah?
那他就更是个蠢货了
More fool him, then.
操你妈
Fuck you!
你现在要干什么 嗯？
What are you gonna do now?
你就这么点能耐么？
Is that all you got?
这是个错误
This was a mistake.
不会再发生这种事了
This never happens again.
真可惜
Shame.
你跟我在一起很合适 你不觉得吗？
You and me go nicely together, don't you think?
你跟我什么事也没有
You and me are nothing.
可要是我下次再不乖呢？
But what if I misbehave again?
你会好好"教训"我的 对吧
You gotta keep me disciplined, haven't you?
别试探我 女人
Don't test me, girl.
我警告你
I'm warning you.
你会后悔的
You'll be sorry.
别紧张
Relax.
谁说男人不能占有 自己想要的奴隶了？
Where's it say a man can't have his slaves if he wants?
我还能杀了她们
I can kill them too,
只要我愿意
if I want.
你可以
You can.
你喜欢做什么都行
You can do anything you like.
优利亚家族的阿提娅
Atia of the Julii,
我要求主持公道
I call for justice.
优利亚家族的阿提娅
Atia of the Julii,
我要求主持公道
I call for justice.
优利亚家族的阿提娅
Atia of the Julii,
我要求主持公道
I call for justice...
我投降 我投降 我投降
I give up. I give up! I give up!
优利亚家族的阿提娅
Atia of the Julii,
我要求主持公道
I call for justice.
优利亚家族的阿提娅
Atia of the Julii,
我要求主持公道
I call for justice.
优利亚家族的阿提娅
Atia of the Julii
- 我要求主持公道 - 那就来吧
- I call for justice. - Here, then!
我就在这儿 你这疯婆娘
Here I am, you crazy bitch!
放完屁就滚蛋 我在这儿呢
Speak your piece and then be gone. Here I am!
冥界诸神
Gods below...
我赛维莉娅
I am Servilia
来自最古老 最神圣…
of the most ancient
优尼亚家族
and sacred Junii,
用血肉筑起罗马七圣山的…
of whose bones the seven hills of Rome are built.
我召唤你们听我一言
I summon you to listen.
诅咒这个女人
Curse this woman.
让苦恼与绝望
Send her bitterness and despair
终伴她一生
for all of her life.
入口之食皆无
Let her taste nothing
化为烙铁和尘土
but ashes and iron.
冥界诸神
Gods of the Underworld,
我仅有的一切
all that I have left
全都献给您作贡品
I give to you in sacrifice
只要您能让我如愿
if you will make it so.
我的天啊
My God.
这倒不失为一种解脱
Now that is an exit.
过来 进里面来
Come. Come back inside.
她死了
She's dead.
所有公民注意
All citizens be aware
附属国的希律王子
that the vassal Prince Herod,
加利利的执行官 [见圣经·路加福音第三节]
Tetrarch of Galilee,
已经来到了罗马
has come to the city.
按照三名执政官的命令
By order of the Triumvirate,
在他到访期间
during his residence here,
所有嘲笑犹太人和他们真主的行为
all mockery of Jews and their one God
应须适度减少
shall be kept to an appropriate minimum.
我听说 罗马的上等人不会索要贿赂
I am told Roman gentlemen do not solicit bribes.
人们必须献上贿赂当作礼物 这是真的吗？
One must offer the bribe as a gift. Is that so?
是的
Yes.
是的 是真的
Yes, that is so.
恐怕我们是最可怕的伪君子
We are the most dreadful hypocrites, I'm afraid.
那我就给你们一份礼物
I offer you a gift, then.
帮我拿下朱迪亚的王位
Help me take the throne of Judea,
与我同仇敌忾 我就会给你们送上一份厚礼
make my enemies your enemies, and I offer you a substantial gift.
这礼能有多厚？
How substantial would this gift be?
需要有多厚？
How substantial does it need to be?
2万磅黄金
20,000 pounds of gold.
成交
Done.
我说我们真该多要点
I said we should have asked for more.
当然 你必须保证
You must guarantee, of course,
管好你的人民
to keep your Jews in line.
他们都很听话… 不然就会自食其果
They will do as I say, or they will suffer the consequences.
那恭喜你 希律
Congratulations then, Herod.
你得到了罗马这个强力的后盾
You have the full backing of Rome.
请教一个问题
One question.
- 说 - 我们的朋友 屋大维和莱彼德斯
- Yes. - Our friends, Octavian and Lepidus.
他们也同意了？
You speak for them too?
是的 我们口径一致
I do. We speak with one voice.
所以他们不会再向我索要 属于他们的那份"礼物" 对吗
So they will not come to me later expecting gifts of their own?
- 不 不会 你的礼物归我们3人所有 - 很好
- No, your gift is for all of us. - Good.
令人羡慕啊 朋友之间能如此信任
Wonderful to have such trust between friends.
这就叫做早起的鸟儿有虫吃
That is what I call a good morning's work.
确实如此 早起的鸟儿有虫吃
Indeed. A good morning's work.
请问我能分得一杯羹吗？
May I inquire what my share will be?
分享？分享什么？
Share? Share of what?
希律的"礼物"
Of Herod's gift.
- 什么礼物？- 啊 我了解了
- What gift? - I see.
是吗？
Do you?
我重申一下
Let me be clear.
没有什么礼物
There was no gift.
希律今天到这儿来 是讨论关于橄榄园…
Herod came here today to discuss administrative issues
征收管理税的问题
of taxes on olive groves,
还有边防抵御 帕提亚人的事宜
of border defenses against the Parthians.
- 没有什么礼物 - 我明白了
- There was no gift. - I understand.
真的吗 伯斯卡
Really, Posca,
自从你获得自由之身
ever since you got your freedom,
你就变得贪婪无比
you have become insufferably greedy.
回家去 好好吃上一顿饭
Go home, have a good lunch,
和你那年轻美貌的妻子做做爱
make love to your pretty young wife,
别老总想着 从别人兜里捞钱
but do stop grubbing about after other people's money.
相信我 这样对你更有意义
Trust me, you'll be far more content.
人渣
Scum.
杂种 人渣
Bastard scum!
当街咒骂他有什么好处？
What good is shouting at him on the street?
真幼稚 只会自找麻烦
It's childish. You'll only get into trouble.
我告诉你 他比他父亲还要坏
He's worse than his father.
不把人民变成奴隶和拜偶像者之前 他是不会善罢甘休的
He'll make our people slaves and idolaters.
他真该死 杂种 去死吧
He should die. The bastard should die!
那无疑是为民除害了
Well, it would be a mitzvah, no doubt.
我说真的
I'm serious.
拜托 就凭我们俩？
Come on. Us?
除了我们 还有谁
If not us, then who?
我们和希律身处一处
Herod is here. We are here.
人民的未来掌握在你我手中
The future of our people is in our hands.
你好 米西纳斯
Salve, Maecenas.
你好 伯斯卡
Hello, Posca.
能谈一下吗？
Might I have a word?
如果你坚持的话
I suppose, if you must.
在我印象里你是那种
It strikes me you're the sort of man
懂得如何保守秘密的人
that knows how to keep a confidence.
是的
Yes.
如果有人告诉你一个…秘密
If a man were to tell you something in confidence,
你也许会把它告诉给其他人… 但不会透漏其来源 对吗
you might tell others, but you would not reveal your source.
不会
No.
多半你也是那种 会给告密者…
And perhaps you're the sort of man that knows how to properly...
适当的酬劳…
reward...
对吗
those who confide in him.
你很了解我
You have me exactly.
你也很会看人
You're a fine judge of character.
你买来的狮子毫无用处
Those lions you bought me were useless.
对拉车一窍不通 还把一个好马夫的手臂给生扯下来
Wouldn't pull my chariot for shit and bit the arm off a perfectly good groom.
畜生通常喜怒无常
They are temperamental animals.
很幸运 我刚抓到一头长颈鹿
I am very fortunate to have a giraffe,
您是否感兴趣？
should you be interested.
我要长颈鹿做什么
What would I do with a giraffe?
骆驼 如何？
Camels, perhaps?
骆驼？你以为我卖枣子的吗？
Camels? Do I look like a fucking date merchant?
要能跑的狮子
Lions that run!
滚出去
Get out.
有什么新闻吗 年轻的凯撒
Now, what news, young Caesar?
20 000的三分之一有多少
What is one-third of 20,000?
6666左右
6,666 or thereabouts.
你当我是傻子吗？
Do you take me for a fool?
一个接一个 毫无根据的问题
Question after question.
让我很难回答你
Makes for very poor conversation.
受到什么委屈 说出来就是
If you have a grievance, just say what it is.
我们曾经有个协定
We had an agreement.
- 平分所有国家收入 - 是的
- We would share all revenue. - Yes.
希律答应给你 20 000磅金子
Herod has agreed to give you 20,000 pounds of gold.
我要我的那部分
I want my share.
谁告诉你这些的？
Who told you this?
你不承认？
You deny?
- 谁告诉他的 - 我收买了希律的手下
- Who told him? - I've bought one of Herod's people.
你还要否认吗？
Do you deny it?
既然希律如此慷慨的送我一份大礼
If Herod is kind enough to give me a gift,
和你们有什么关系？
what business is it of yours?
礼物不属于国家收入吧
A gift is not revenue.
那不是礼物 是贿赂 作为政治和军事上的照顾
It is not a gift. It is a bribe for political and military favors,
这些照顾却要国家来承担
the cost of which favors shall be borne by the state.
- 迂腐 - 面对现实吧
- Pedantry. - Let us be realistic.
这份协定将会失效…
This arrangement of ours cannot work
如果你总是借机…
if you seek every opportunity
背着我中饱私囊的话
to aggrandize yourself at my expense.
中饱私囊？
Aggrandize myself?
说这话的人 还把自己"所谓的"父亲
This from the boy who... whose so-called father
称之为神
has been declared a god.
这头衔他受之无愧
An honor he well deserves.
这么说是因为你 想让别人把你当作神的儿子
You only did it so that you might be known as the son of a god.
你没有一点自己的功绩
You have no accomplishments of your own,
就借别人的光
so you seek to borrow the glory of others.
是的 在穆提那打败你… 算不得什么功绩
It's true. It was no accomplishment to defeat you at Mutina.
你战胜我？
You defeated me?
你这个懦夫犊子
You cowardly little shit!
他连帐篷都没搭过
He'd never even left his tent.
你自始自终都没战胜过我
You have never defeated me in anything.
先生们 不要激动
Gentlemen, gentlemen, let's not get overheated.
我们一定能够达成某种合理的协议
I'm sure we can come to some kind of reasonable agreement.
我以为你会吸取教训… 学会谦卑与自律
I had hoped you might have learned some humility and discipline.
照今日看 你仍然是… 粗鲁 傲慢的好色之徒
I see now that you are still the same crude, arrogant lech
本性难改
you always were.
没错 还是老样子
That's right, just the same.
还在操你母亲
And still fucking your mother!
你没事吧？
Are you all right?
是的 没事
Yes, nothing.
- 要不躺下歇会？- 不 没事
- Do you want to go lie down? - No, it's fine.
还需要什么吗 女主人
Anything else, Mistress?
水
Water.
主人呢？
Master?
不 什么都不要
No. Nothing.
看见没？现在变成好奴才了
See? Good slave now,
自从你给她一顿揍之后
ever since you gave her a good beating.
你说的没错
There you go.
你该每个月都赏她一顿
You should beat her the same way every month.
如果她在我回来前醒来 告诉她我去了莱蒂的神殿
If she wakes before I'm back, tell her I've gone to Lyde's temple.
再和我讲讲那个农场 都会买些什么牲畜
Tell me again about the farm. What kind of animals will we have?
绵羊
Sheep,
山羊
goats,
- 猪啊 - 没有鸡？
- pigs. - And chickens?
买啊 还有马 如果你喜欢再买些大象
Yes, horses as well. Elephants, if you like.
- 冥神之子 请你… - 怎么了？
- Sons of Dis, will you... - What's the matter?
对不起 不是说你 只是…
I'm sorry. It's not you, it's...
生意上的问题
It's business matters...
别管了
Forget it.
给我个香吻
Give me a kiss.
你还爱我吗？
Do you still love me?
当然
Of course.
非常的爱
Very much.
奥米博 我找你…
Omnipor, I've been looking...
真抱歉
Oh, excuse me.
- 这不是… - 不是的
- Is that... - It's nobody.
只是个女仆 你在外面等我吧
It's just a girl. I'll see you outside.
- 这是卢西尔斯·乌瑞纳斯的女儿 - 不 不是的
- That's the daughter of Lucius Vorenus. - No, it's not.
少糊弄我 难道是我眼瞎了？
Don't fuck me about. I've got eyes, haven't I?
你们在一起多久？
How long's this been going on?
几个月
A few months.
你傻吗 姑娘 你不知道这样 对你父亲是多么不敬吗？
Are you insane? You know what disrespect this shows your father?
- 我不在乎 我恨他 - 不过如果他查到 你知道什么后果
- I don't care. I hate him. - But think what will happen if he finds out.
只要我在他面前百依百顺 他会觉得诸事顺利
If I smile at him and serve his damn soup like a good daughter, he thinks it's fine.
- 他是不会发现的 - 他不会吗？
- He won't find out. - Will he not?
我们是结盟立誓的教友 我要对他以诚相待 我得告诉他
Him and me are friends by oath. It is my duty to be honest with him. I'll have to tell him.
- 不能 你不能告诉他  - 对不起 孩子
- You can't. You can't tell him! - Sorry, love, but if I don't tell him
如果我不告诉他 我不就是和你们同流合污？
I'm just as guilty as you two, aren't I?
如果他从其它途径得知此事 他决不会相信…
And what if he finds out? He'll never believe I didn't know.
他宝贵的女儿与我手下有一腿 而我却一无所知
His precious daughter and one of my men.
他会把我给生吞了
He'll have my guts!
真是乱七八糟
This is a right fucking mess.
求你了 先生 别告诉他
Please, sir, don't tell him.
他会杀了她的
He'll kill her.
不 我想他还不至于如此
No, he won't go that far, I shouldn't think.
会的 你了解他的
Yes, he will. You know him.
他是个畜生 杀了我母亲 也会杀我
He's an animal. He killed my mother. He'll kill me.
但你要我怎么做？你让我陷入…如此尴尬的境地
But what am I to do? You've put me in an impossible position here.
只要你不告诉他 我干什么都行
I'll do anything you say. Just please don't tell him.
我不知道
I don't know.
也许…
Maybe.
我可以帮你
Maybe I can help you out.
谢谢
Thank you.
你能为我做点事作为回报吗？
Would you do something for me in return?
任何事
Anything.
我们有不少生意上的来往
Me and him do a lot of business together.
如果你能留意一下…
If you kept your ears and eyes open,
他的一举一动
told me what was going on,
那便对我很有帮助
that would be very helpful to me.
我会的
I can do that.
好孩子
Good girl.
就这么说定了
It's settled, then.
- 希律的礼物将分为三份 - 减去佣金
- Herod's gift will be shared three ways. - Minus a finder's commission.
二位都同意在任命… 行政官以上级别的官吏前先与对方协商
Each of you will consult the other before naming any officials above aedile rank.
这协议也包括外邦首领 王子 国王等等
The same goes for the appointment of foreign chieftains, princes, kings and so forth.
从现在起收到的所有钱
Now, all monies received,
包括国家税收 通关税 战利品
including taxes, customs revenue, military spoils
以及非正式的赠品和贿赂等等
and informal gifts and bribes,
都要收归国库
will be placed in the treasury
全由土星的祭司负责掌管
under the supervision of a Saturnine priest.
很好
Fine.
你们俩握手言和吧
And now you must shake hands.
好样的 重归于好了
Lovely. Friends again.
- 没有想象中的难 对吧 - 不
- That wasn't so hard, was it? - No.
没其他事的话 我还有公务要办
If we're all done, I have work to do.
你没意识到你俩的争吵 会让城内人心惶惶？
You do realize your two bickering has put the whole city in a panic?
我会让新闻官去宣布
I'll have the newsreader say something,
"重建友好盟约"之类的
"Renewed vows of amity" and so forth.
没人会相信新闻官说所的
No one believes what the newsreader says.
你有更好的建议吗？
You have some notion you wish to suggest?
我有
I do.
如果我们两家能喜结连理
If a marriage was to happen between our two houses,
人民就不会再有疑虑了
no one could doubt all was well.
就算意大利化成了灰…
Well, I don't care if all Italy burns,
我也不要嫁给这小子
I'll not marry him.
主意不错
It's not a bad idea.
是表达团结的最有力方式
It would be a strong expression of unity.
民众喜欢喜庆的婚礼
And the plebs love a good wedding.
我没理由拒绝
I have no objection.
谢谢 谅你也不敢
Thank you. I should think not.
还要再商榷一下
We should discuss it, at least.
我们可以在牧神节之后举行婚礼 讨个吉利
We could do it after Lupercalia. It's very auspicious.
怎么了？
What?
如果我们要讨论政治联姻 妇女就该退下
If we are to discuss a marriage contract, it's inappropriate for a woman to be present.
是 抱歉 你们继续
Yes, sorry. Carry on.
不过一定要给我 足够的时间做嫁衣打扮得光彩照人些
Be sure to leave enough time for my dressmaker to make me something nice.
是的 母亲
Yes, Mother.
我要结婚了
I'm getting married.
安东尼和我准备结婚了
Antony and I are getting married.
奥克塔维娅在哪?
Where's Octavia?
[犹太传教士咏颂希伯来经文]
安东尼的婚礼于明天举行
This wedding of Antony's tomorrow...
我刚听说 那个希律狗也会出席
I've just heard the dog Herod will be there.
到场的还有1000名贵族 身边会有扈从 还有士兵随行
Him and a thousand other aristos. There'll be lictors all over, soldiers as well.
他们的注意力都集中在新人身上 不会有人在意希律的
Watching the bride and groom, nobody will be paying any mind to Herod.
场面肯定吵杂 拥挤不堪
There'll be a big crowd, lots of noise.
而且混乱 是个绝佳的机会
Chaos. It's the perfect time.
我不确定
I don't know.
你吓破胆了 是吗？
You're not losing your nerve, are you?
- 没有 - 我们发过誓
- No. - We made an oath on the Torah.
我没有放弃誓言 我只是想说
And I'll not break it. I'm just saying,
我们要求稳 机会只有一次
we've got to be sure, we only get the one chance.
机会已经来了
This is it!
谁知道呢？
Who knows?
幸运的话 只要明天有足够的人群 我们或许还能活着回来
If we're lucky and the crowd's thick, we might even make it out alive.
那是不可能的
No. There's no chance of that.
即时我们早被坎成肉泥了
We'll be hacked to pieces quick as Pan.
那他也活不成
His will be done.
明日见分晓
Tomorrow, then.
过来 孩子们
Come, children.
叶什
Yesh.
- 你在做什么？- 你吓到我了
- What are you doing? - You scared me.
我有事找你 但你不在
I was looking for you, but you weren't here.
现在我在了
Here I am.
你没事吧？发烧了？
Are you all right? You look feverish.
不 我没事
No, no, I'm good.
你想要什么
Now, what do you need?
没什么
Nothing.
妹妹想买条新裙子
Sister needs a new dress.
她比芥菜长得还快啊？
She grows like mustard.
谢谢 父亲
Thank you, Father.
不给我点什么？
Nothing for me?
我爱你
I love you.
我们得谈谈
We need to talk.
是的
Yes, we do.
我想我们该分开一阵子
I was thinking we should take a little break.
- 分开？- 暂时不做爱了
- A break? - From sex.
直到我们新婚之夜
Just until our wedding night.
我想让我们的新婚之夜 过得与众不同
I want our wedding night to be something special.
你不同意？
Don't you agree?
还有很多事需要讨论一下
And we have so many practical things we need to discuss...
首先 我们准备住在哪 我很乐意搬到你的别墅去
Where we're going to live. I'm happy moving into your villa,
不过它真的需要 从头到脚的装修一遍
but it will need to be redecorated from top to bottom.
而后我要你卖掉你的奴隶
And I insist you sell your slaves,
那些以前被你干过的红男绿女
male or female, whom you've previously fucked.
- 阿提娅 我… - 我坚持
- Atia, I... - I insist.
还有件事 你还未给我买新婚礼物
And another thing, you still haven't bought me my wedding gift.
我有话要说
I need to talk.
好吧 不打断你了
Well, I'm not stopping you.
不论她生病或是健康 富有或贫穷
When and where you are Gaia,
我始终忠于她
I, then and there, am Gaius.
不论他生病或是健康 富有或贫穷
When and where you are Gaius,
我始终忠于他
I, then and there, am Gaia.
[拉丁语]
为何如此沮丧
Why so gloomy?
没什么 有点头痛而已
No reason. A bit of a headache.
可怜的阿提娅 是吧？我都觉得她可怜 嗯
Poor Atia. I feel for her.
我一直都以为她跟安东尼之间是纯粹的利益关系 可你看看她
I always thought her attachment to Antony was purely practical, but look at her.
我认为这个老女人是真的爱上他了
I think the old girl's genuinely in love with him.
屋大维为什么要这么做？
Why did Octavian do this?
很简单
Simple.
奥克塔维娅更容易怀上孩子
Octavia is more likely to provide children.
如果不是为了生孩子 那婚姻还有什么必要？
And what is marriage, if not a machine for the production of babies?
这是不对的
It's wrong.
这是个错误
It's just wrong.
小心点 朋友 不知道的人…
Careful, friend. Anyone who didn't know better
会以为你爱上奥克塔维娅了呢
might think you were in love with Octavia.
祝福你
Blessings upon you.
我宁可去吃屎
I'd rather eat shit.
请抛弃欲望 把眼光放远些
Please try to see beyond your own desires.
我可不能让你嫁给安东尼
I couldn't very well let you marry Antony.
谁都知道你们俩是情人
Everybody knows you were lovers.
公众会猜测那样的婚姻… 只是出于情感和肉欲
The public would assume it was a marriage of mere sentiment, of lust.
而明眼人都能看出 这是政治团结的象征
Whereas this match is clearly a political statement of unity.
- 阿提娅 - 走开
- Atia. - Go away.
你不能留在这里 客人们会猜想你到底去哪儿了
You cannot stay in here. Our guests will wonder where you are.
叫他们见鬼去吧
Well, our guests can go and fuck themselves.
这也是无可奈何的事
There was no choice.
你儿子也没别的办法
Your son would have it no other way.
难道他是你主人吗？
And he is your master?
他是我政治上的伙伴 政治要求…
He is my political partner. Policy dictates that...
去他妈的政治 直说吧
Policy be damned. Speak plain.
你爱权利比爱我还深
You love power more than you love me.
这是两码事
They are two completely different things.
这场婚姻跟我们之间毫无关系
This marriage has nothing to do with us.
什么都没变
It changes nothing.
爱情 你跟我
Love, and you and I...
什么也没变
It changes nothing.
哦 我明白了 你先是背叛了我 然后你又提议要背叛我的女儿
I see. First you betray me and now you propose to betray my daughter.
恕我失陪
Forgive me.
你准备好了吗？
Are you ready?
我们走吧
Let's go.
- 等等 - 他们来了
- Wait. - They're coming!
我很抱歉 我干不了这个
I'm sorry, I can't do it.
什么？
What?
不要再杀人了 希律只不过是个普通人 他的死无足轻重
No more killing. Herod is just a man. His death is useless. It's just more blood.
如果我们杀了他 会有别人取代他
If we kill him, another will take his place.
- 来一个杀一个 - 我做不到
- We'll kill him too. - Not by my hand.
你发过誓的
Listen, you made an oath.
我只能违背了
I break it, then.
兄弟
Brother...
我有妻子与儿女
I have a wife. I have children.
你这个胆小鬼 可怜的胆小鬼
You're a coward, a sniveling coward.
一直如此
You always were.
那么我一个人来
I'll do it alone, then.
不要
No. No!
兄弟
Brother!
你…
You...
不是…
are not
我兄弟
my brother.
挺别扭的 不是吗？
This is strange, isn't it?
听着 我…
Look, I...
我知道你并不高兴 但是…
I know you're not exactly happy about all this, but...
今晚是新婚之夜
it is our wedding night.
做你想做的
Do as you like.
你能不能…
Well, if you wouldn't mind just...
让苦恼与绝望
Send her bitterness and despair
终伴她一身
for all of her life.
入口之食皆无
Let her taste nothing
化为烙铁与尘土
but ashes and iron.
我要串叶松香草和藜芦
I need silphium and hellebore.
这么快便怀上了
You caught it early.
对
Yeah.
喝下这个…
Drink this...
在睡觉前…
before bed...
等你早晨
and when you wake
醒来…
in the morning,
烦恼便一扫而空
problem is over.
味道怎么样？
How's it taste?
我不喜欢口味重的
I hate strong flavors.
放在柳叶茶里 就不会有味道了
If you put it in willow tea, you won't taste it at all.
给你些马尾以防失血过多
I'll give you some horsetail in case there's much bleeding.
那不用了
No, that's all right.
我不需要那玩意
I don't need that.